Guide to the Stanley Thomas Williams Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Stanley Thomas Williams papers
1917-1969
MS 557
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3
(5 boxes)
Correspondence, notes, lectures, writings, and miscellanea relating to the academic career and literary works of Stanley T. Williams, a Yale University professor of American literature, including notes on several prominent American authors.
Williams, Stanley Thomas, 1888-1956
Biographical / Historical
Stanley T. Williams (1888-1956): educator; B.A., Yale, 1911, M.A., 1914, Ph.D., 1915; instructor at Yale, 1915-1917, 1919-1920, 1920-1926, associate professor, 1926-1932, professor, 1932-1956; author of many books.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, notes, lectures, writings, and miscellanea relating to the academic career and literary works of Stanley T. Williams, a Yale University professor of American literature, including notes on several prominent American authors.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Authors, American; Literature -- History and criticism; Literature -- Study and teaching -- United States; Educators; Alsop, Richard; Brainard, John G. C. (John Gardiner Calkins), 1796-1828; Wildman, Thomas G. (Thomas Gregory), 1837-1891; Williams, Stanley Thomas, 1888-1956; Yale University -- Faculty
- Inventory, Circa 1917-1955
  - I Photostats: folded sheets of which the first is marked 1818; a journal starting 1 Mar 1828; 2 separate sheets. (Possibly photostats of notes for Washington Irving's Sketchbook .) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - II Report on lecture series given at the University of Mexico, 1947 December (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - III Student paper on Hawthorne's The Scarlet Letter, 1928; ALS copy of Milt Gross' parody of "The Raven" in hand of E. W. Lewis, Y'28; Notes on English 57, 5 Feb 1947-1928 May 1947, taken by Robert B. Graves, Y'47Mar. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - IV Bibliography of STW's published works, 1917-Apr 1944. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - V A Collection of Published Melville Letters, prepared by English 378, University of Chicago, Summer Quarter, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - VI Papers and tests relating to English 36 and English 52, 1924 November 10-1930 November 3 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - VII Examinations in English 56, 57, and 157, 24 Mar 1950 - 28 Oct 1955; Bibliography, Nathaniel Hawthorne, undated; Henry James Revisions, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - VIII Fragmentary notes for English 39, 1928 January 11-1941 April 30 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - IX Fragmentary notes for English 57, 1943 January 20-1955 September 26 (Box 1A, Folder 1-2)
  - X Typescripts of book reviews, Undated (Box 1A, Folder 3)
  - XI "Honours" list of authors by assignment week, 1 Oct 1923 - 22 May 1924 List of anthologies, undated (Box 1A, Folder 4)
  - XII TLS to STW from Frank MacShane, 1954 December 11 (Box 1A, Folder 5)
  - XIII Notes for various outside lectures, 1924 January 23-1949 April 23, undated (Box 1B, Folder 1-50)
  - XV 2 marking books (one unused), 1954 October 11-1955 January 10 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - XVI 1 box, with role of microfilm of photostats of STW's articles for a book (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - XVII Lectures in England and Germany
    - "The Poetry of Edgar Allan Poe", London, 1936 April 16 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - "Washington Irving and Germany", Halle, 4 May, Berlin 15 May, 1936 May (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - "New Light on Washington Irving", Berlin, 1936 May 8 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - The American Struggle for Intellectual Independence, Munich, 29 Apr, Hamburg, 11 May, Berlin, 15 May, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - XVIII Richard Alsop; Y'1798h: photostats of his correspondence, and correspondence concerning his life, 1926 October 18-1927 June 9 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - XIX Brainard, John G. C.,Y'1815, notes, bibliographies, and copies of his correspondence. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - XX Lectures
    - "The Literature of the Frontier", Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "The Sketch Book", 1943 November 23, 1944 November 21 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "The Spanish Background of American Literature", 1954 November 22 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "Macauley", 1931 January 7 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - XXI Folder labeled "Commencement Lectures - STW"
    - "Individualism", Oslo, Norway, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "Phi Beta Kappa", Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "Courage", Taft School, 1935 January 20 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "Conquest of Fear", Taft School, 1937 September 20 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "On Yale's Endowment Fund", Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "The Good and Great for Company": Our Literary Heritage, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "His Father's Saying", Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "Educated", Milwaukee Country Day School, [illegible], 1926 June 10 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 15 pages of typed ms, on European judgements of American literature, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "Old Tragedies and New Books", North Carolina College for Women, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "The Undergraduate and the Classroom", Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - at Hotchkiss School, 1930 June 15 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - to Sigma Xi, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - XXII Learned Articles
    - "The Last Plays of Richard Cumberland, 1785-1813", Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Hard Gem-Like Flame", Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Introduction to a volume on Irving, Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Stevenson as a Critic", Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "The literary Criticism of William [illegible] Caldwell Roscoe", Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Empedocles on Etna", Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "J. S. Mill as a Critic of Literature", Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Yeast: A Victorian Curiosity", Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - 4 pages [illegible] ms., untitled, Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - XXIII Manuscripts
    - Thoreau, Undated (Box 2A, Folder 1)
    - Whitman, Undated (Box 2A, Folder 1)
    - Emerson, Undated (Box 2A, Folder 2)
    - Hawthorne, Undated (Box 2A, Folder 3)
    - Hawthorne's First Novel, Undated (Box 2A, Folder 3)
    - pp. 3, 5 ff on Cooper and Irving, Undated (Box 2A, Folder 3)
  - XXIV Manuscripts
    - Paper on the Spanish background of American literature, Undated (Box 2A, Folder 4)
    - Preface to book on American literature for Europeans, 1953 August 1 (Box 2A, Folder 4)
    - Paper on fishing in Cape Cod ponds, Undated (Box 2A, Folder 4)
    - "In Defense of the Literary Pilgrim", Undated (Box 2A, Folder 4)
    - "Matches", Undated (Box 2A, Folder 4)
    - "Absent from Vermont" (poem), Undated (Box 2A, Folder 4)
    - "Apologia and Riposte" (poem), 1944 March 8 (Box 2A, Folder 4)
    - "Coming Events", Undated (Box 2A, Folder 4)
    - "Irving, Washington", Undated (Box 2A, Folder 4)
      General
      Probably Ms. of article for Encyclopedia Americana.
    - STW's edition of Thomas Danforth's "Journal of My Visit to Virginia", Undated (Box 2A, Folder 4)
    - "American Scholars and American Literature", Undated (Box 2A, Folder 5)
    - "On Re-reading Herman Melville" (2 copies), Undated (Box 2A, Folder 5)
    - Paper on Edward Arlington Robinson, Undated (Box 2A, Folder 5)
    - Paper on development of American literature, Undated (Box 2A, Folder 5)
    - pp. 2-12 of paper on Washington Irving, Undated (Box 2A, Folder 5)
    - 6 handwritten pages on Sweden, Undated (Box 2A, Folder 5)
    - "A Parody on the Gothic Romance" (Box 2A, Folder 5)
  - I Ralph Waldo Emerson, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    One envelope containing 16 packets of notes.
  - II Thomas G. Wildman
    - 44 typed copies of his correspondence, 1859 April 15-1865 July 24 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Additional typed copies of his correspondence with notes, 1858 August 11-1881 January 12, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Notes on correspondence, Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence and memos concerning publishing of Wildman letters, 1945-1947, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - III Envelopes containing notes on:
    - "Gentlemen of the U.S. Military Academy", Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
      Apparently a lecture on S. Benet.
    - Aldis Collection, Undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
      American bellelettresistic literature.
    - American literature of the Civil War, 1926 February 17 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      No class number provided.
    - Bibliography: general, Undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Books to look up. By author, Undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Brown, C. B., Undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Bryant, Undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
      3 packets of miscellaneous notes.
    - Cather, Willa: The Personality of Willa Cather, Undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Contemporary American literature, 1926 May 24-26 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      2 packets of notes (revised).
    - Contemporary fiction, Undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
      Fragmentary notes, by themselves.
    - Cooper, Undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
      2 packets of notes.
    - Dickinson, Emily, Undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Dreiser VI: Dreiser and the Cult of Naturalism, Undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Early colonial literature: bibliography, Undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Edwards, Jonathan, 1923 October 9, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
      3 packets of notes, one of which is dated - Honors.
    - Edwards and Mather, Undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
      Notes, clipped together, and perhaps used together.
    - Faulkner, Undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
      Notes on books about him.
    - Franklin, Benjamin, Undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Frost, Robert, Undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
      One set marked "English 56. Modern American Poetry 2. Frost." No year indicated.
    - Harte, Undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Hawthorne (Box 3A, Folder 1)
    - Holmes, Undated (Box 3A, Folder 2)
    - Howells, Undated (Box 3A, Folder 2)
    - Irving, Washington, Undated (Box 3A, Folder 2)
    - James, Henry, 1926 May, undated (Box 3A, Folder 2)
      Many packets of miscellaneous notes; only one set is dated, but with no indication for what class.
    - James, Henry: The Tragic Muse (read August 1938), Undated (Box 3A, Folder 3)
    - Knickerbocker poets, Undated (Box 3A, Folder 3)
    - Lanier, 1925 April 20, undated (Box 3A, Folder 3)
      Contains bibliography, notes for April 20, 1925 (without any indication for which class), and 2 packets of miscellaneous notes.
    - Lindsay, Undated (Box 3A, Folder 3)
    - Longfellow, Undated (Box 3A, Folder 3)
      I packet of lecture notes and 4 mimeographed pages ( 3 of poems; 1 of 7 paragraphs)
    - Lowell, Undated (Box 3A, Folder 4)
      3 packets of notes.
    - Melville (Box 3A, Folder 4)
    - O'Henry, 1926 May 10, 1933 April 26 (Box 3A, Folder 5)
      Revised for 1926 and partially revised for 1933, with no indication of class.
    - Paine, Thomas, Undated (Box 3A, Folder 5)
      Possible bibliography and some notes.
    - Parkman (Los Angeles), 1924 July 25 (Box 3A, Folder 5)
    - Poe, Undated (Box 3A, Folder 5)
    - Poetry, 18th century, undated (Box 3A, Folder 5)
    - "Poetry" notes, Undated (Box 3A, Folder 6)
    - Plotinus, Undated (Box 3A, Folder 6)
    - Steinbeck, Undated (Box 3A, Folder 6)
      Fragmentary notes.
    - Stowe, Harriet B.: Uncle Tom's Cabin, Undated (Box 3A, Folder 6)
    - Thoreau, Undated (Box 3A, Folder 6)
    - Wharton, Edith, Undated (Box 3A, Folder 7)
      Miscellaneous notes.
    - "What Is an American?", Undated (Box 3A, Folder 7)
    - Whitman, 1949 January 3, undated (Box 3A, Folder 7)
      Miscellaneous notes and "discards" from 1949.
    - Whittier, Undated (Box 3A, Folder 7)
  - Letters to George P. Clarke, 1947-1955 (Box 3A, Folder 8)
  - Notes for English 56, not complete, 1941 October 29-1955 January 12 (Box 4)
    Full list in box.
  - Notes for English 56, not complete, 1955 September 16-November 25 (Box 4)
    Full list with notes in box.
  - Notes for English 156, not complete, 1944 May 16-1955 November 14 (Box 4)
  - Note for English 36: Hawthorne, 1931 February 10 (Box 4)
  - Notes for English 157, incomplete (Box 4)
    - Poe, 1941 May 13, 1953 May 12
    - Emerson, 1954 October 19
    - Melville, 1954 November 30
    - Whitman, Undated
  - Assorted notes, class not given, 17 Jul 1924 - 9 Feb 1945 (Box 4)
  - Notes for unidentified classes (Box 4)
    - Holmes, 1924 July 22, 1926 February 22
    - authors by assignment weeks, Sep 16-Jan 17 (no year), Undated